<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>The Fay Lab</title>
<link>https://thefaylab.com/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://thefaylab.com/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.31</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Community engaged teaching and learning fellowship</title>
  <dc:creator>Gavin Fay</dc:creator>
  <link>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-06-04-engagedteaching-gf/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="community-engaged-teaching-and-learning-fellowship" class="level1">
<h1>Community engaged teaching and learning fellowship</h1>
<p>I (Gavin) joined the university’s <a href="https://www.umassd.edu/leduc/about/resources/faculty/">community engaged teaching and learning faculty fellowship program</a> in September 2024. A two year program run by the <a href="https://www.umassd.edu/leduc/">Leduc Center for Civic Engagement</a>, the fellowship brings faculty at the university together via a series of scaffolded programming, discussion, and collaborative work sessions to help faculty interested in developing or extending service learning opportunities as part of their pedagogy and in their courses. As someone who integrates community members within my teaching and has a public-service focus to my service work at the university (primarily but not solely at supporting the regional fisheries assessment and management processI have been hoping to take part in this program for several years. For various reasons this hasn’t panned out but this year I signed up. With an idea of perhaps expanding our stock assessment practicum course into something more structured and sustainable, and to add some additional elements to my science communication course.</p>
<p>The first year of the fellowship involved monthly meetings with our cohort (new fellows in AY24 and last year’s new fellows), following amazing and thoughtful new programming developed by Leduc director Matt Roy and <a href="https://faculty.providence.edu/en/persons/nicholas-v-longo">Nick Longo</a>, faculty at Providence College, with short preparatory readings and videos, facilitated small- and large-group reflections on materials and understanding of motivations . We touched on a range of topics, including “Building Reciprocal Partnerships when designing Community-engaged courses”, “Assessing Impact when Reflecting on Community-Based Teaching &amp; Learning”,&nbsp; “Facilitating Better Discourse”, and “Asset-Based approach for Centering Community”. Making space and time for intentional thinking about how we do this work is so important, and I really appreciated the time that Matt and Nick put into investing in this space and facilitating these conversations with us. Crucially, this programming also connects me with colleagues in other Colleges at the university to learn from each other - often in our teaching we (faculty) are the only ones in our role in the room. I find so often that these sessions and the readings named things that we all are already doing in our classes and service work, but that the common language helped us talk through things together. I’ve also been excited to use some of the readings/videos in my class and share these with my students directly. Thanks to Nick and Matt for allowing us to share these resources this way (Forking as a worldview).&nbsp; I am looking forward to implementing some of the ideas I developed ‘out loud’ with my colleagues this year in a revised model for our stock assessment practicum course in the upcoming academic year.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blog</category>
  <category>community</category>
  <category>training</category>
  <guid>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-06-04-engagedteaching-gf/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-06-04-engagedteaching-gf/service-learning_leduc.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="179" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Conversations with recreational fishers about fisheries science</title>
  <dc:creator>Kamran Walsh</dc:creator>
  <link>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-03-25-recfishconv-kaw/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="conversations-with-recreational-fishers-about-fisheries-science" class="level1">
<h1>Conversations with recreational fishers about fisheries science</h1>
<p>This past fall, PhD student Kamran Walsh (me) teamed up with He Lab Master’s student Kevin Bennett to interview recreational fishers throughout the southern New England area. This was part of Gavin’s Science Communication class, with the specific purpose of our exercise being to better understand how anglers in our community view science and management decisions. Our interviews were more conversational than formal, with topics touching upon past and ongoing research related to New England recreational fisheries, social justice issues in the community, and fisheries outside of New England. We ultimately wanted to provide an informal, safe setting for both scientists and stakeholders to learn from each other’s experiences and discuss their views. As someone who has fished nearly his whole life and seen plenty of conflict involving the shared use of marine resources, I was especially interested in learning about how other anglers feel about the work that SMAST and other nearby research institutions are engaging in.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Over the course of several weeks that extended through the end of the 2024 recreational saltwater fishing season in New England, Kevin and I interviewed a diverse group of anglers and industry members in a variety of settings along Massachusetts’ South Coast, Cape Cod, and coastal Rhode Island. This included purely recreational anglers, charter captains, tackle store owners, tackle company employees, and even software developers of a new smartphone app geared towards improving recreational fisheries data collection. We learned that angler and industry members’ opinions towards research and management vary, particularly involving controversial regulations such as Striped Bass recreational measures. We also were pleasantly surprised to learn that the anglers we interviewed were often highly supportive of conservation efforts and research, with multiple interviewees expressing their support for current (even more restrictive) regulations and increased fisheries enforcement. Each of the people that we talked to had unique views towards fisheries that were heavily influenced by their cultural background, worldview, and way of life. It is also worth noting that anglers expressed nearly unanimously negative views towards offshore wind for a host of reasons, stressing the importance of accounting for this friction point in the future of ocean usage allocation and marine resources management. Ultimately, it was an enriching experience that provided an ideal environment not only to learn about anglers’ honest opinions of science and management, but the region’s fisheries and fishing cultures through the unique perspectives provided.&nbsp; You can view the videos <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DypQZYaEhcK0&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cgfay%40umassd.edu%7C97e2a7b9387046dc2c0a08dd566fb6a5%7C328d6c0d0f2f4b7693109762ba1c3e2d%7C0%7C0%7C638761760008081003%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=ISd2goVKPtvAcIw7g4R9aJb6Vvvrh%2FCJw3%2BHT1YZn2Q%3D&amp;reserved=0">here</a> (part 1), <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DYTgYDcP8YYo&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cgfay%40umassd.edu%7C97e2a7b9387046dc2c0a08dd566fb6a5%7C328d6c0d0f2f4b7693109762ba1c3e2d%7C0%7C0%7C638761760008112177%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=k2znX2FGecxjBia3GGAoNKVH1pzW6HejxPV1rKRpyyE%3D&amp;reserved=0">here</a> (part 2), <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DMGIMuxh-fx4&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cgfay%40umassd.edu%7C97e2a7b9387046dc2c0a08dd566fb6a5%7C328d6c0d0f2f4b7693109762ba1c3e2d%7C0%7C0%7C638761760008125400%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=DfXYqkrPAGjHhZQxlQfM7Srz%2Fq9nbbK%2BPmjhc1IVBb0%3D&amp;reserved=0">here</a> (part 3), <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DlJhn8W6N8rA&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cgfay%40umassd.edu%7C97e2a7b9387046dc2c0a08dd566fb6a5%7C328d6c0d0f2f4b7693109762ba1c3e2d%7C0%7C0%7C638761760008137330%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=ooMwTBDcXBrevtrDz86SncSa8qX1nk1aLQ2GToY5B1o%3D&amp;reserved=0">here</a> (part 4), and <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DjZT47_bfxgg&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cgfay%40umassd.edu%7C97e2a7b9387046dc2c0a08dd566fb6a5%7C328d6c0d0f2f4b7693109762ba1c3e2d%7C0%7C0%7C638761760008149131%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=AZ5PzSFCNQRB2VRCx9q6M7KJyYDZCqWxmFORAioN7Qo%3D&amp;reserved=0">here</a> (part 5).</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blog</category>
  <category>communication</category>
  <guid>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-03-25-recfishconv-kaw/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-03-25-recfishconv-kaw/recfishconv-yt-thumb-keb.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="106" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
