<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>The Fay Lab</title>
<link>https://thefaylab.com/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://thefaylab.com/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.26</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Safety and Survival Training by Fishing Partnership at SMAST</title>
  <dc:creator>Rowan Ignatius</dc:creator>
  <link>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-24-safetytraining-ri/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="safety-and-survival-training-at-smast" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-and-survival-training-at-smast">Safety and Survival Training at SMAST</h2>
<div style="float: right; position: relative; top: 0px; padding: 10px;">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-24-safetytraining-ri/flares.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
<p>On Thursday, October 16, 2025, I attended the Fishermen Safety and Survival Training conducted by SMAST and Fishing Partnership Support Services (FPSS) at New Bedford’s waterfront. The workshop convened researchers, commercial fishermen, and recreational anglers for essential emergency preparedness instruction. Offered at no cost to participants, this reflects FPSS’s sustained commitment to advancing safety standards.</p>
<p>Fishing, whether commercial or recreational, remains one of the most perilous professions and pastimes. The industry’s inherent risks underscore the importance of comprehensive safety training. The workshop provided participants with practical, hands-on experience in critical survival techniques, including accessing Emergency Position Indicating Radio Beacons, Signal Flares, MAYDAY Calls, Man Overboard Recovery, Firefighting, Flooding &amp; Damage Control, Opioid Overdose Response, Survival suits and distress signaling techniques. As several fishermen shared stories of life-threatening situations they had faced at sea, including man-overboard (MOB) incidents. Hearing these firsthand accounts really made me realize the critical importance of this training.</p>
<p>Russell Kingman and Nathan Winterson, my instructors for the day, made the class engaging, funny, and interesting, while still effectively teaching essential life-saving skills, making it easier to absorb critical information that could one day save lives. In addition, FPSS provided all participants with Narcan opioid overdose sprays, further supporting preparedness for emergencies both at sea and ashore.</p>
<p>I am looking forward to the CPR and First Aid training that will be hosted by FPSS on January 13, 2026, at Fort Tabor Community Center, New Bedford, MA.</p>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="2">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-24-safetytraining-ri/tank1.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-24-safetytraining-ri/tank2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blog</category>
  <category>students</category>
  <category>training</category>
  <guid>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-24-safetytraining-ri/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-24-safetytraining-ri/tank1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2025 ICES Annual Science Conference, Klaipėda</title>
  <dc:creator>Kamran Walsh and Sophie Wulfing</dc:creator>
  <link>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-22-ices-asc-2025-kawsw/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="ices-annual-science-conference-klaipėda" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ices-annual-science-conference-klaipėda">2025 ICES Annual Science Conference, Klaipėda</h2>
<p>Between September 15-18, Gavin, Kam and Sophie attended the <a href="www.ices.dk">International Council for the Exploration of the Seas (ICES)</a> 2025 Annual Science Conference in Klaipėda, Lithuania. Here, we were joined by other SMAST faculty, staff, students, and alumni and learned all about the fascinating fisheries research happening around the world. It was very inspiring to meet brilliant marine scientists from all over the world and learn about their exciting ongoing work. Kam presented a talk on the Summer Flounder recreational fishery Management Strategy Evaluation, and Sophie was asked last-minute to give a lightning talk on my poster about different treatments of environmental covariates in yellowtail flounder stock assessment projections. SMAST student Sierra Richardson and recent alum Cole Carrano also presented posters on Monkfish catch-per-unit-effort (CPUE) standardization and incorporating environmental effects in Atlantic Bluefin Tuna Stock Assessment. It was our first time in Eastern Europe, and some of our favorite parts of the conference were learning about Baltic food, music, and history, exploring the Curonian Spit on the coast, and walking through an underwater tunnel surrounded by giant Sturgeon at the Lithuanian Sea Museum.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-22-ices-asc-2025-kawsw/smastklaipeda.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>UMass and SMAST students, staff, faculty, and alumni at ICES ASC 2025</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-22-ices-asc-2025-kawsw/kamtalk.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Kam giving a talk on summer flounder MSE.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-22-ices-asc-2025-kawsw/sophietalk.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Sophie giving a lightning talk on decision making in projecting environmental covariates for yellowtail flounder.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-22-ices-asc-2025-kawsw/kamaquarium.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300"></p>
<figcaption>Kam becoming one with the fishes at the Lithuanian Sea Museum.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blog</category>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>students</category>
  <category>travel</category>
  <guid>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-22-ices-asc-2025-kawsw/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-10-22-ices-asc-2025-kawsw/smastklaipeda.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Learning from our summer interns</title>
  <dc:creator>Sophie Wulfing and Kamran Walsh</dc:creator>
  <link>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-09-12-nbhsinterns-sw/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="learning-from-our-summer-interns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="learning-from-our-summer-interns">Learning from our summer interns</h2>
<p>This summer, the Fay Lab had the opportunity to mentor three interns from New Bedford High School. They worked closely with Kam, Sophie, and Sarah to help progress current projects in the Fay Lab including a mangrove restoration project, a science communication project, and a project analyzing the effects of predation and competition on winter flounder survival. On top of that, interns attended a weekly R Bootcamp to hone their coding skills and learn the basics of data analysis. They also attended a Science Communication workshop during the final week of the internship. All interns gave a final presentation about their projects at the end of the internship. They all did a fantastic job with their projects and we wish them the best with whatever they decide to pursue in the future! We also asked them to write a short reflection of their time at SMAST:</p>
<p><strong>Gavin:</strong></p>
<div>
<div style="float: left; position: relative; top: 0px; padding: 10px;">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-09-12-nbhsinterns-sw/gavin.png" class="img-fluid" width="250"></p>
</div>
<p>My experience as a SMAST intern was one of much personal growth and finding out who I am. I learned I love to code while at SMAST. I attended coding workshops every Wednesday and also my personal project was one mostly consisting of coding. I was taught R because it is good for data analysis. At first it was a lot and trying to wrap my head around all of the technical parts of my project. But thanks to my lab supervisor, Kamran I was able to help out with his project and figure out how to use R a decent amount considering the short amount of time we spend together on the project. And speaking of my lab. The Fay lab was an amazing group of people I got to work with during my time here. They all made the experience so much more enjoyable and interesting and you can clearly see they are all good friends and work pretty well together. We definitely shared a good amount of laughs during our lab meetings and also I learned what a meeting experience is like as well. Which is going to help me in my future as well. Orientation week was also a lot of fun and educational as well. We got to get an overview of many different projects that are going on at SMAST other than just the one I ended up working on. I learned so much like when we brought up lobster traps every morning from the pier to look at what species we caught. I was able to learn so much about different species of animals that are around me and how to identify them. We also learned so much from the presentations we were able to sit through throughout the week. So much information that just solidified my love for the ocean. Every project is cool and interesting in its own way. I would have been lucky to be a part of any one of them. Even though I really liked the one I was a part of. Overall, this internship taught me a useful skill (coding), taught me what a 9-5 is like, and left me with memories I will never forget.</p>
</div>
<div>
<div style="float: right; position: relative; top: 0px; padding: 10px;">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-09-12-nbhsinterns-sw/piper.png" class="img-fluid" width="250"></p>
</div>
<p><strong>Piper:</strong></p>
<p>As I walked into the SMAST building for the first time a feeling resonated with me telling me that this is where I want to be. While first this notion was strong and sudden, the light that stemmed from it did not dim, instead it grew. The first week at SMAST quickly began to foster and care for this light, teaching me a variety of lessons; communication, how to survive a sinking ship, how to pick up a lobster, and so much more, lessons I vow to carry with me for the next five weeks. In such an inviting atmosphere I grew increasingly comfortable by the second, always being encouraged to ask questions and talking to people with crazily impressive qualifications. These conversations gave me the realization that the academic path is winding and never ending, showing me that no matter which way I lead myself, as long as I am constantly in a state of learning, I am doing the right thing. As I look back on my time at SMAST I find myself overwhelmingly appreciative of the amazing experiences the internship gave me, the incredible lessons and skills I learned over my time here including coding and proper scientific communication. As well as relationships that I will cherish with me as I continue down the marine science path, both through the people who acted as role models and the friendships that I found on field trips or even sitting in my cubicle. Having done many marine programs in my life I can confidently say the SMAST internship, the building and the people inside are very special.</p>
</div>
<p><strong>Amaya:</strong></p>
<div>
<div style="float: left; position: relative; top: 0px; padding: 10px;">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-09-12-nbhsinterns-sw/amaya.png" class="img-fluid" width="250"></p>
</div>
<p>At the beginning of this internship in July 2025, starting at SMAST felt like a whole new world in the sense of marine science. I, as well as the other high school interns felt immediately welcomed by the SMAST community. In just the first couple days I learned so much from the scientific names of sea creatures to learning how to put on survival suits in under 60 seconds. The introduction to SMAST was educational and eye opening but also was fun and light hearted. With what I learned in just the first few days I knew this is definitely something that I want to pursue, which I did not know walking in. As I continue on with this internship, I am excited to learn more about the different options of professions connected to marine fisheries and how what we do at SMAST directly helps the local people of New Bedford, as well as all over the world. I am looking forward to engaging with the marine science community while learning new skills that I can apply in academic and real world situations.</p>
</div>
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-09-12-nbhsinterns-sw/labinterns.png" class="img-fluid"> (<a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DNGrt2btix8/">Learn more about SMAST’s high school internship program</a>).</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blog</category>
  <category>community</category>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>training</category>
  <category>students</category>
  <guid>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-09-12-nbhsinterns-sw/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-09-12-nbhsinterns-sw/labinterns.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Floundering around in Virginia - DISES annual project meeting</title>
  <dc:creator>Sophie Wulfing</dc:creator>
  <link>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-08-20-framevirginia-sw/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="floundering-around-in-virginia---dises-annual-project-meeting" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="floundering-around-in-virginia---dises-annual-project-meeting">Floundering around in Virginia - DISES annual project meeting</h2>
<p>Gavin, Kam, and I (Sophie) traveled to Hampton, VA in May to join the first annual project team meeting for our NSF Dynamics of Integrated Socio-Environment Systems (DISES) award: <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2408987"><em>Dynamics of socio-environmental factors driving resilience of coastal fisheries: integrating feedbacks between livelihoods, human behavior, climate, and fish ecology</em></a>. As climate change has been shown to shift the distribution of summer flounder, this project aims at using stakeholder input and interviews to understand the socio-ecological dynamics of the summer flounder fishery in the US Atlantic Coast. The ultimate goal of this interdisciplinary group (led by PI Dr.&nbsp;Holly Kindsvater at Virginia Tech) is to understand the factors that influence human decision-making, including when people choose to fish for flounder, where they choose to fish, and their understanding and compliance with local regulations. At the two-day meeting, we discussed strategies for finding and interviewing fluke anglers, identified relevant stakeholders, and set up logistics and goals for this 5 year project. We also set our working group name to be <strong>Flounder Research for Actionable Management and Engagement</strong>, or <strong>FRAME</strong>. During the meeting, Kam gave a presentation to the group on the predicted outcomes of different management strategies on summer flounder stocks and fishery productivity. In our free time, we enjoyed lots and lots of seafood and checked out the Air and Space Museum. Also walking along the beach after the meeting, we saw a large colony of Black Skimmers. According to a very enthusiastic passerby, this was the largest colony of skimmers that the area had seen in years. Overall, it was a great trip that set the groundwork for some very interesting research.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-08-20-framevirginia-sw/frame-hampton-2025.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>FRAME project team at the May 8-9 2025 meeting in Hampton Virginia. Back row (left to right): Mike Sorice, Craig Ramseyer (co-PI), Holly Kindsvater (PI), Willa Chaves (co-PI), Fernando Goncalves (co-PI), Kam Walsh. Front row (left to right): Jonathan van Senten, Akea Cader, Sophie Wulfing, Hailey Conrad, Mary Adebote, Gavin Fay (co-PI)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-08-20-framevirginia-sw/conrad-talk.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>PhD candidate Hailey Conrad (VT) presents her research during the May 2025 FRAME meeting</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-08-20-framevirginia-sw/skimmers.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The black skimmers!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In early July, Kam and I also joined Akea Cader, a graduate student from Virginia Tech, for two weeks of interviewing summer flounder anglers in Massachusetts. We interviewed anglers in Plymouth, Cape Cod, and locations around Buzzards Bay (including here in New Bedford) to better understand the recreational fishing culture of Massachusetts, the popularity of summer flounder as a target catch, and peoples’ motivations for fishing. As a data scientist, it was really interesting to see how more qualitative data is collected and analyzed and I got to visit many wonderful beaches and shorelines around Massachusetts. A huge thank you to Akea for showing us around and best of luck on your research!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-08-20-framevirginia-sw/fluke-research-akea-july2025.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Sophie Wulfing and Kam Walsh assist VT PhD student Akea Cader conduct angler interviews in coastal Massachusetts. Photo credits: Akea Cader and Kam Walsh (top-right)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>(This project is NSF Award # 2408987. <a href="https://thefaylab.githubio/frame">Visit the FRAME project website here</a>).</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blog</category>
  <category>community</category>
  <category>research</category>
  <guid>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-08-20-framevirginia-sw/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-08-20-framevirginia-sw/frame-logo-2.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="75" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>ARROW - Summer Education Accelerator (SEA)</title>
  <dc:creator>Catalina Roman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-06-10-arrowsea-cr/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="arrow---summer-education-accelerator-sea" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="arrow---summer-education-accelerator-sea">ARROW - Summer Education Accelerator (SEA)</h2>
<p><img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-06-10-arrowsea-cr/arrow_01.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>At the end of May, the Academic Center for Reliability and Resilience of Offshore Wind (<a href="https://arrowosw.org/">ARROW</a>) held its first <a href="https://arrowosw.org/empower/summer-education-accelerator-sea/">Summer Education Accelerator (SEA)</a> workshop at the University of Massachusetts Amherst. This event brought together faculty, students, lab researchers, and professionals from across industry, government, and academia to explore key topics shaping the future of offshore wind energy. The SEA workshop was designed not only to foster technical skills but also to promote cross-sector collaboration and systems thinking around the complex challenges and opportunities of offshore wind development. It was also a great opportunity to link students and faculty in person across the many ARROW <a href="https://arrowosw.org/about/">partner institutions</a>. A team of UMass Dartmouth faculty and six of UMassD’s 8 ARROW graduate student fellows (including our lab’s own Gavin Fay and Catalina Roman) took part in the workshop.&nbsp;</p>
<p>One of the first themes of the workshop was offshore wind power systems and how they integrate with the regional electrical grid. Led by Professor <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=d9sp-qkAAAAJ&amp;hl=en&amp;inst=8491034277084204831">Golbon Zakeri</a>, participants used an ISO New England grid simulator to explore real-world challenges in balancing renewable energy inputs with grid stability. This hands-on activity was complemented by a field trip to the <a href="https://www.iso-ne.com/">ISO New England</a> control center and the <a href="https://www.hged.com/smart-energy/clean-energy/hydro/default.aspx">Holyoke Gas &amp; Electric Dam</a>, offering an up-close look at how energy is managed at the infrastructure level. On the engineering front, students examined the design and reliability of monopiles, which form the structural foundation of many offshore wind turbines. With guidance from <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dennis-hindhede/">Dennis Hindhede</a> and Professor <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=TIEVrr8AAAAJ&amp;hl=es&amp;inst=8491034277084204831">Benjamin Schafer</a>, participants delved into engineering principles, structural dynamics, and common failure modes. This session emphasized the importance of long-term reliability and risk management in the harsh conditions of offshore environments. Rounding out the week, Professor <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=ApZKT_0AAAAJ&amp;hl=es&amp;inst=8491034277084204831">Gavin Fay</a> introduced a systems-thinking approach to marine spatial planning. In this session, participants engaged in participatory modeling exercises that simulated the tradeoffs involved in managing ocean space for multiple uses, including offshore wind, fisheries, and conservation. The activity emphasized the role of inclusive decision-making and ecosystem-based frameworks in supporting sustainable development.</p>
<p>Throughout the week, the SEA workshop served as a collaborative space where technical knowledge, policy considerations, and environmental insights intersected. As the offshore wind sector continues to grow, programs like SEA play a vital role in equipping the next generation of scientists, engineers, and decision-makers to approach this transition with both innovation and resilience. What stood out to me most was the diversity of participants, not only in terms of academic backgrounds, but also cultural perspectives. It was exciting to meet people from across the country, including fellow Latin Americans and to have moments where I could share and connect over research in my first language. Coming from a biology background, I found some of the more technical engineering topics challenging at first, but the hands-on activities made them much more approachable and engaging. Visiting the ISO New England control room and the Holyoke Dam helped ground the grid integration concepts in the real world, and I particularly enjoyed the interactive experiments on monopile fatigue and structural resistance (turns out testing paper “piles” can be surprisingly fun). My favorite part, unsurprisingly, was exploring the tradeoffs in marine spatial planning, a topic close to my research and one that brought together ecological thinking with decision making. It was interesting to see how different groups prioritized things according to their previous knowledge. I left the workshop feeling inspired, more connected to this growing community and excited about the upcoming meeting and outputs.&nbsp;</p>
<p><br>
<img src="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-06-10-arrowsea-cr/arrow-sea-montage-cr.png" class="img-fluid"><em>Top left:</em> Keith Hankowsky, Ki-Hwan Kim, Alison Frey, Catalina Roman, Adriano Giangiardi and Andie Painten atop Mt. Sugerloaf; <em>Bottom left:</em> Holyoke Dam in the Connecticut River ; <em>Right:</em> Hands-on activity about managing ocean space for multiple uses.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blog</category>
  <category>training</category>
  <category>offshore-wind</category>
  <category>students</category>
  <guid>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-06-10-arrowsea-cr/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-06-10-arrowsea-cr/ARROW-Final-Logo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="84" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Community engaged teaching and learning fellowship</title>
  <dc:creator>Gavin Fay</dc:creator>
  <link>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-06-04-engagedteaching-gf/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="community-engaged-teaching-and-learning-fellowship" class="level1">
<h1>Community engaged teaching and learning fellowship</h1>
<p>I (Gavin) joined the university’s <a href="https://www.umassd.edu/leduc/about/resources/faculty/">community engaged teaching and learning faculty fellowship program</a> in September 2024. A two year program run by the <a href="https://www.umassd.edu/leduc/">Leduc Center for Civic Engagement</a>, the fellowship brings faculty at the university together via a series of scaffolded programming, discussion, and collaborative work sessions to help faculty interested in developing or extending service learning opportunities as part of their pedagogy and in their courses. As someone who integrates community members within my teaching and has a public-service focus to my service work at the university (primarily but not solely at supporting the regional fisheries assessment and management processI have been hoping to take part in this program for several years. For various reasons this hasn’t panned out but this year I signed up. With an idea of perhaps expanding our stock assessment practicum course into something more structured and sustainable, and to add some additional elements to my science communication course.</p>
<p>The first year of the fellowship involved monthly meetings with our cohort (new fellows in AY24 and last year’s new fellows), following amazing and thoughtful new programming developed by Leduc director Matt Roy and <a href="https://faculty.providence.edu/en/persons/nicholas-v-longo">Nick Longo</a>, faculty at Providence College, with short preparatory readings and videos, facilitated small- and large-group reflections on materials and understanding of motivations . We touched on a range of topics, including “Building Reciprocal Partnerships when designing Community-engaged courses”, “Assessing Impact when Reflecting on Community-Based Teaching &amp; Learning”,&nbsp; “Facilitating Better Discourse”, and “Asset-Based approach for Centering Community”. Making space and time for intentional thinking about how we do this work is so important, and I really appreciated the time that Matt and Nick put into investing in this space and facilitating these conversations with us. Crucially, this programming also connects me with colleagues in other Colleges at the university to learn from each other - often in our teaching we (faculty) are the only ones in our role in the room. I find so often that these sessions and the readings named things that we all are already doing in our classes and service work, but that the common language helped us talk through things together. I’ve also been excited to use some of the readings/videos in my class and share these with my students directly. Thanks to Nick and Matt for allowing us to share these resources this way (Forking as a worldview).&nbsp; I am looking forward to implementing some of the ideas I developed ‘out loud’ with my colleagues this year in a revised model for our stock assessment practicum course in the upcoming academic year.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blog</category>
  <category>community</category>
  <category>training</category>
  <guid>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-06-04-engagedteaching-gf/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-06-04-engagedteaching-gf/service-learning_leduc.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="179" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Conversations with recreational fishers about fisheries science</title>
  <dc:creator>Kamran Walsh</dc:creator>
  <link>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-03-25-recfishconv-kaw/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="conversations-with-recreational-fishers-about-fisheries-science" class="level1">
<h1>Conversations with recreational fishers about fisheries science</h1>
<p>This past fall, PhD student Kamran Walsh (me) teamed up with He Lab Master’s student Kevin Bennett to interview recreational fishers throughout the southern New England area. This was part of Gavin’s Science Communication class, with the specific purpose of our exercise being to better understand how anglers in our community view science and management decisions. Our interviews were more conversational than formal, with topics touching upon past and ongoing research related to New England recreational fisheries, social justice issues in the community, and fisheries outside of New England. We ultimately wanted to provide an informal, safe setting for both scientists and stakeholders to learn from each other’s experiences and discuss their views. As someone who has fished nearly his whole life and seen plenty of conflict involving the shared use of marine resources, I was especially interested in learning about how other anglers feel about the work that SMAST and other nearby research institutions are engaging in.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Over the course of several weeks that extended through the end of the 2024 recreational saltwater fishing season in New England, Kevin and I interviewed a diverse group of anglers and industry members in a variety of settings along Massachusetts’ South Coast, Cape Cod, and coastal Rhode Island. This included purely recreational anglers, charter captains, tackle store owners, tackle company employees, and even software developers of a new smartphone app geared towards improving recreational fisheries data collection. We learned that angler and industry members’ opinions towards research and management vary, particularly involving controversial regulations such as Striped Bass recreational measures. We also were pleasantly surprised to learn that the anglers we interviewed were often highly supportive of conservation efforts and research, with multiple interviewees expressing their support for current (even more restrictive) regulations and increased fisheries enforcement. Each of the people that we talked to had unique views towards fisheries that were heavily influenced by their cultural background, worldview, and way of life. It is also worth noting that anglers expressed nearly unanimously negative views towards offshore wind for a host of reasons, stressing the importance of accounting for this friction point in the future of ocean usage allocation and marine resources management. Ultimately, it was an enriching experience that provided an ideal environment not only to learn about anglers’ honest opinions of science and management, but the region’s fisheries and fishing cultures through the unique perspectives provided.&nbsp; You can view the videos <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DypQZYaEhcK0&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cgfay%40umassd.edu%7C97e2a7b9387046dc2c0a08dd566fb6a5%7C328d6c0d0f2f4b7693109762ba1c3e2d%7C0%7C0%7C638761760008081003%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=ISd2goVKPtvAcIw7g4R9aJb6Vvvrh%2FCJw3%2BHT1YZn2Q%3D&amp;reserved=0">here</a> (part 1), <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DYTgYDcP8YYo&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cgfay%40umassd.edu%7C97e2a7b9387046dc2c0a08dd566fb6a5%7C328d6c0d0f2f4b7693109762ba1c3e2d%7C0%7C0%7C638761760008112177%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=k2znX2FGecxjBia3GGAoNKVH1pzW6HejxPV1rKRpyyE%3D&amp;reserved=0">here</a> (part 2), <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DMGIMuxh-fx4&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cgfay%40umassd.edu%7C97e2a7b9387046dc2c0a08dd566fb6a5%7C328d6c0d0f2f4b7693109762ba1c3e2d%7C0%7C0%7C638761760008125400%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=DfXYqkrPAGjHhZQxlQfM7Srz%2Fq9nbbK%2BPmjhc1IVBb0%3D&amp;reserved=0">here</a> (part 3), <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DlJhn8W6N8rA&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cgfay%40umassd.edu%7C97e2a7b9387046dc2c0a08dd566fb6a5%7C328d6c0d0f2f4b7693109762ba1c3e2d%7C0%7C0%7C638761760008137330%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=ooMwTBDcXBrevtrDz86SncSa8qX1nk1aLQ2GToY5B1o%3D&amp;reserved=0">here</a> (part 4), and <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DjZT47_bfxgg&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cgfay%40umassd.edu%7C97e2a7b9387046dc2c0a08dd566fb6a5%7C328d6c0d0f2f4b7693109762ba1c3e2d%7C0%7C0%7C638761760008149131%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=AZ5PzSFCNQRB2VRCx9q6M7KJyYDZCqWxmFORAioN7Qo%3D&amp;reserved=0">here</a> (part 5).</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blog</category>
  <category>communication</category>
  <guid>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-03-25-recfishconv-kaw/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-03-25-recfishconv-kaw/recfishconv-yt-thumb-keb.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="106" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A new era for lab updates, and a look back on 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Kamran Walsh, Gavin Fay</dc:creator>
  <link>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-03-03-update2024-kaw/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="a-new-era-for-lab-updates-and-a-look-back-on-2024" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-new-era-for-lab-updates-and-a-look-back-on-2024">A new era for lab updates, and a look back on 2024</h2>
<p><em>Kamran Walsh</em>, with contributions by <em>Gavin Fay</em></p>
<p>We’ve been doing some reflection during our lab meetings early this year, on many things, and including reflection on and revision to our lab values and how we express these and our culture in our lab manual (co-working on revising, affirming, and clarifying language describing our lab philosophy, with pushes to come). Part of these conversations included a group interest in being more intentional in making visible our lab activities via this blog on our website. Lab members have been drafting posts on things they have been doing that we hope to share out over the next few months. PhD student Kamran Walsh also put together a ‘2024 highlight reel’, some of which others will expand on but seems good for a (not exhaustive) winter warmer recap:</p>
<p>Megan Winton (now Dr.&nbsp;Megan Winton) successfully defended her dissertation “Integrating telemetry data to improve abundance estimates and management advice for a highly migratory marine predator” in spring 2024. Megan’s defense was a fantastic culmination of her work which included her <a href="https://www.umassd.edu/news/2023/shark-study-published.html">2023 publication on an integrated population model for the Cape Cod white sharks</a>.</p>
<p>Decision support specialist Madeleine Guyant started a full time Global Fisheries Specialist position at The Nature Conservancy (TNC) as part of <a href="https://fishpath.org/about#core-team">the Fishpath team</a>, and Master’s student Angelia Miller started a full time position at the <a href="https://www.nefmc.org/">New England Fisheries Management Council (NEFMC)</a>. We also welcomed Sarah Hope to the lab, a Master’s student who is investigating the intersection of supply chain and ecosystem dynamics to inform management decisions and improve access to local seafood in New England.</p>
<p>Gavin <a href="https://wfc2024.fisheries.org/2023/02/07/onboarding-fisheries-scientists-to-open-science-integrating-collaborative-and-inclusive-principles-into-education-workforce-development-and-community-management/">co-organized a session at the World Fisheries Congress</a>in Seattle in March with <a href="https://jules32.github.io/">Julie Lowndes</a> (<a href="https://openscapes.org/">Openscapes</a>) and Eli Holmes (NOAA Fisheries, <a href="https://nmfs-opensci.github.io/">NMFS Open Science</a>), which included a panel discussion and ‘unconference’ on “Onboarding Fisheries Scientists to Open Science”.</p>
<p>PhD student Maria Cristina P<strong>é</strong>rez presented lab work on developing machine-learning emulators of complex marine ecosystem models to evaluate Ecosystem-Based Fisheries Management at the <a href="https://www.umassd.edu/news/2024/marine-undersea-technology-must-technical-review.html?_gl=1*mba0hs*_gcl_au*ODI1MjQ2MTAwLjE3MzU5MTUzMjA.">annual UMassD Marine and UnderSea Technology (MUST) conference</a>.</p>
<p>Fay Lab members were also involved in numerous research projects and working groups in 2024 that supported decision-making for sustainable management of living marine resources on the US east coast. Gavin continued his service on the Mid-Atlantic Fishery Management Council’s Scientific and Statistical Committee, contributed to the Northeast state-space methods research track which passed peer review, and chaired the SouthEast Data, Assessment, and Review (SEDAR) Red Drum peer review. Kamran and Gavin led work on a Management Strategy Evaluation aimed at characterizing the predicted outcomes of different summer flounder recreational fishery management decisions in collaboration with the NOAA Northeast Fisheries Science Center, the Mid-Atlantic Fishery Management Council, and the Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission (ASMFC). Kamran also presented some of this work at the <a href="https://imssymposium2024.sites.umassd.edu/">2024 Intercampus Marine Science Research Symposium</a>. With collaborator Kate Masury (<a href="https://www.eatingwiththeecosystem.org/">Eating with the Ecosystem</a>), Sarah and Gavin ran a “markets into models” workshop and interviews with our advisory board of seafood business representatives as part of NOAA Saltonstall-Kennedy funded work to understand seafood supply chains.</p>
<p>The Fay Lab also engaged in work that contributed towards the UMass Dartmouth graduate student community, stakeholder involvement in research, visibility of women in STEM, and science education. Master’s student Luca McGinnis (<a href="http://www.cfrfoundation.org/">now at the Commercial Fisheries Research Foundation</a>) operationalized the UMass graduate student union to advocate for fair working conditions and wages for the university’s graduate student workforce. Sarah led an “Into the Deep” workshop aimed at starting meaningful conversations between scientists, managers, fishers, and other stakeholders about contemporary issues and conflicts that New England’s fisheries face. PhD student Catalina Roman and Kamran continued the lab’s long ongoing QuantFish workshop series, a platform for sharing ongoing quantitative fisheries research to scientists of all career stages.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Overall, it was an exciting and productive year for the Fay Lab. Despite the challenges that fisheries are currently facing, we plan on diving headfirst into these challenges to provide innovative solutions for ensuring the long-term productivity of living marine resources and the communities that depend upon them. Keep your eyes peeled for more Fay Lab updates!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blog</category>
  <category>community</category>
  <category>communication</category>
  <guid>https://thefaylab.com/blog/2025-03-03-update2024-kaw/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://thefaylab.com/images/thefaylab_hex.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="155" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
